Guide to the William Gilman Thompson Autograph Collection
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
William Gilman Thompson autograph collection
1771-1924
MS 484
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
3
(1 box, 1 folio)
Collection of autograph letters and photographs accumulated by Thompson, a physician.
Thompson, W. Gilman (William Gilman), 1856-1927
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of the William G. Thompson estate, 1939.
Biographical / Historical
Physician; Ph.B., Yale, 1877; received his M.D. degree from Columbia in 1881; in 1885 won the Joseph Mather Smith prize for an essay on the valves of the heart; in 1887 became visiting physician of the New York Hospital until 1894, and of the Presbyterian Hospital until 1912; in 1887 became professor of physiology at the University of the City of New York, remaining until 1898; 1898-1916, professor of medicine at Cornell University Medical College.
Scope and Contents
Collection of autograph letters and photographs accumulated by Thompson, a physician.
Autographs; Lin-Fu-Yeh; Aoki, Shūzō, 1844-1914; Bancroft, George, 1800-1891; Beeckman, Robert Livingston, 1866-1935; Billings, John S. (John Shaw), 1838-1913; Bismarck, Otto, Fürst von, 1815-1898; Bolling, John Randolph; Booth, Maud Ballington, 1865-1948; Bright, John, 1811-1889; Bryant, William Cullen, 1794-1878; Bryce, James Bryce, Viscount, 1838-1922; Bülow, Bernhard Ernst von, 1815-1879; Butler, Nicholas Murray, 1862-1947; Carlisle, George William Frederick Howard, Earl of, 1802-1864; Choate, Joseph Hodges, 1832-1917; Clark, Edward Tracy, 1878-1935; Cobden, Richard, 1804-1865; Curtis, George William, 1824-1892; Dexter, Franklin Bowditch, 1842-1920; Farragut, David Glasgow, 1801-1870; Farrand, Livingston, 1867-1939; French, Daniel Chester, 1850-1931; Gilman, Daniel C. (Daniel Coit), 1831-1908; Gladstone, W. E. (William Ewart), 1809-1898; Godkin, Edwin Lawrence, 1831-1902; Gompers, Samuel, 1850-1924; Gorgas, William Crawford, 1854-1920; Greeley, Horace, 1811-1872; Guggenheim, Daniel, 1856-1930; Guyot, A. (Arnold), 1807-1884; Hadley, Arthur Twining, 1856-1930; Hammond, John Hays, 1855-1936; Hammond, John Hays, 1888-1965; Heiser, Victor G. (Victor George), 1873-1972; Hobson, Richmond Pearson, 1870-1937; Holmes, Oliver Wendell, 1809-1894; Jacobi, A. (Abraham), 1830-1919; Lepsius, Richard, 1810-1884; Lincoln, Mary Todd, 1818-1882; Livingston, Robert Livingston, 1866-; Mayo, William James, 1861-1939; McAneny, George, 1869-1953; McKinlay, Kenneth G.; Mitchel, John Purroy, 1879-1918; Osler, William, Sir, 1849-1919; Parkhurst, C. H. (Charles Henry), 1842-1933; Payne, Oliver H. (Oliver Hazard), 1839-1917; Pierrepont, Edwards, 1817-1892; Pinchot, Gifford, 1865-1946; Platt, Thomas Collier, 1833-1910; Polk, William Mecklenburg, 1844-; Rockefeller, John D., Jr. (John Davison), 1874-1960; Schurz, Carl, 1829-1906; Seward, William H. (William Henry), 1801-1872; Shaftesbury, Anthony Ashley Cooper, 7th Earl of, 1801-1885; Sherman, William T. (William Tecumseh), 1820-1891; Schurman, Jacob Gould, 1854-1942; Stanley, Arthur Penrhyn, 1815-1881; Stimson, Lewis Atterbury, 1844-1917; Thompson, Joseph P. (Joseph Parrish), 1819-1879; Van Name, Addison, 1835-1922; Viets, Roger, 1738-1811; Virchow, Rudolf, 1821-1902; Wagner, Cosima, 1837-1930; Wagner, Richard, 1813-1883; Welch, William Henry, 1850-1934; White, Andrew Dickson, 1832-1918; Wilson, Woodrow, 1856-1924; Woods, Arthur, 1870-1942
- Inventory, 1771-1924, n.d; .50 linear feet (1 box, 1 folio)
  - Aoki, Shūzō (1844-1914), with photograph, 1879 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Bancroft, George (1800-1891), with photograph, 1873 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Beeckman, Robert Livingston (1866-1935), 1915 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Billings, John Shaw (1838-1913), with photograph, 1910-1913 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Bismarck, Otto, Fürst von (1815-1898), with photograph, 1872-1875 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Bolling, John Randolph, 1923 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Booth, Maud Ballington (Charlesworth) (1865-1948), 1910 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Bright, John (1811-1889), with photograph, 1866 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Bryant, William Cullen (1794-1878), undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Bryce, James Bryce, viscount (1838-1922), photograph only, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Bülow, Bernhard Ernst, von (1815-1879), with photograph, 1874-1878, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Butler, Nicholas Murray (1862-1947), 1919 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Carlisle, George William Frederick Howard, 7 th earl of (1802-1864), 1852 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Choate, Joseph Hodges (1832-1917), with photograph, 1874-1915 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Clark, Edward Tracy (1878-1935), 1924 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Cobden, Richard (1804-1865), with photograph, 1852-1853 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Curtis, George William (1824-1892), with photograph, 1869 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Dexter, Franklin Bowditch (1842-1920), 1902 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Eulenburg, Wendt, Graf zu
    General
    See: box 1, folder 2
  - Farragut, David Glasgow (1801-1870), with photograph, 1869 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Farrand, Livingston (1867-1939), with photograph, 1924 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - French, Daniel Chester (1850-1931), undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Gilman, Daniel Coit (1831-1908), with Photograph, 1907 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Gladstone, William Ewart (1809-1898), with photograph, 1874 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Godkin, Edwin Lawrence (1831-1902), with photograph, 1871 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Gompers, Samuel (1850-1924), with photograph, 1917 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Gorgas, William Crawford (1854-1920), with photograph, 1916 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Greeley, Horace (1811-1872), with photograph, 1864 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Guggenheim, Daniel (1856-1930), 1917 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Guyot, Arnold Henry (1807-1884), [1859?] (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Hadley, Arthur Twining (1856-1930), with photograph, 1917 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Hammond, John Hays (1855-1936), with photograph, 1916, undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Hammond, John Hays, Jr. (1888-1956), 1914 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Heiser, Victor George (1873-1819), 1917 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Hobson, Richmond Pearson (1870-1937), with photograph, undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Holmes, Oliver Wendell (1809-1894), 1885 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Jacobi, Abraham (1830-1919), with photograph, undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Lepsius, Karl Richard (1810-1884), with photograph, 1879 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Lincoln, Mary (Todd) (1818-1882); copy, 1866 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Lin-Fu-Yek, photograh only, 1880, undated (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Livingston, Robert Livingston (1866-), Photograph only, undated (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - McAneny, George (1869-1953), 1915-1918 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - McKinlay, Kenneth G., 1924 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Mayo, William James (1861-1939), with photograph, 1912 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Mitchel, John Purroy (1879-1918), with photograph, 1917 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Osler, William, bart. (1849-1919), with photograph, 1897-1911 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Parkhurst, Cahrles Henry (1842-1933), 1909 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Payne, Oliver Hazard (1839-1917), with photograph, 1914 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Pierrepont, Edwards (1817-1892), 1875 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Pinchot, Gifford (1865-1946), with photograph, 1924 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Platt, Thomas Collier (1833-1910), 1904 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Polk, William Mecklenburg (1844-1918), 1912 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Rockefeller, John Davison, Jr. (1874-1960), with photograph, 1919 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Sannomiya, Y, with photograph, 1879 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Schurman, Jacob Gould (1854-1942), 1913-1916 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Schurz, Carl (1829-1906), with photograph, 1903 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Seward, William Henry (1801-1872), 1861 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Shaftesbury, Anthony Ashley Cooper, 7 th earl of (1801-1885), 1852 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Sherman, William Tecumseh (1820-1891), with photograph, 1864-1884 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Stanley, Arthur Penrhyn (1815-1881), with Photograph, 1863 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Stimson, Lewis Atterbury (1844-1917), undated (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Sturm, ____, undated (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Thompson, Joseph Parrish (1819-1879), 1852-1878 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    See also: box 2
  - Van Name, Addison (1835-1922), 1902 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Viets, Roger (1737-1811), 1771 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Virchow, Rudolph Ludwig Karl (1821-1902), with photograph, 1879 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Wagner, Cosima (Liszt) (1837-1930), 1875 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Wagner, Richard (1813-1883), photograph only
    See: box 1, folder 25
  - Walan, ____
  - Welch, William Henry (1850-1934), with photograph, 1907-1908 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - White, Andrew Dickson (1832-1918), with photograph, 1879, 1912, undated (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Wilson, Woodrow (1856-1924), photograph only
  - Woods, Arthur (1870-1942), 1917 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Unidentified, 1874-1879 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - OVERSIZE
    - Re: Thompson, Joseph Parrish (1819-1879) (Box 2)